Guide to the Joe Campbell Collection of Dorothy Dean Letters MSS.222
Fales Library and Special Collections
Joe Campbell Collection of Dorothy Dean Letters
1964-1987
Fales Library and Special Collections
Dean, Dorothy
Campbell, Joe
MSS.222
0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box.
The Joe Campbell Collection of Dorothy Dean Letters contains 46 letters written to Joe Campbell. Of the 46, 42 were written by Dorothy Dean; the other four were written by various friends of Campbell after Dean's death. The letters are dated from 1964-1987.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Provenance
Received by donation from Callie Angell, Andy Warhol Film Project, Whitney Museum of American Art, 2008. The accession number associated with this gift is 2008.222.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Dean was a downtown social figure. Born into a bourgeois black family in 1932 in White Plains, New York, she attended Radcliffe College and in 1958 earned a masters degree in Fine Arts from Harvard College. While at Cambridge, she began associating almost entirely with gay white men, presumably in an effort to distance herself from the politics surrounding being both black and female in the fifties and sixties, politics with which she did not identify.
Moving to New York, Dean established herself as part of Andy Warhol's Factory and also worked as the door person at Max's Kansas City. She was loved for her strong, verbose personality, perhaps mostly for her playful phrasing and clever nicknames (Andy Warhol, to Dean, became "Drella," a combination of Dracula and Cinderella; James Baldwin was "Martin Luther Queen"). She rarely worked; she held brief editorial and proofreading positions at publications such as The New Yorker and Vogue. She appeared in several Factory films, including My Hustler, and Afternoon.
In 1980, Dean moved to Boulder, Colorado, where she worked at a bookstore and as an editor, and continued writing letters to her friends. She died of cancer in Boulder on February 13, 1987.
Sources:
Als, Hilton. The Women. New York: Farrar Straus Giroux, 1998. pp. 67-117.
Watson, Steven. Factory made: Andy Warhol and the Sixties. New York: Pantheon Books, c2003.
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
The Fred W. McDarrah Gay Pride Photographs Collection (MSS 193)
Scope and Content Note
The Joe Campbell Collection of Dorothy Dean Letters contains 46 letters written to Joe Campbell. Of the 46, 42 were written by Dorothy Dean; the other four were written by various friends of Campbell after Dean's death in 1987, regarding her funeral, obituaries, and a memorial reception held in New York. The letters written by Dean range from 1964 to 1986. The latest letter by Dean dates approximately eight months prior to her death.
A number of the letters contain newspaper clippings, dealing with a range of topics from downtown musicians such as Lou Reed to pivotal moments in the gay rights movement. One letter contains a manuscript of the first issue of Dean's film review, which she called the "All-Lavender Cinema Courier." Evincing her creative and erudite linguistic control, the prose and content of the letters vividly represent Dean's literary wit and personality.
Arrangement
The collection consists of 46 folders, each containing one letter.
The letters are arranged in chronological order.
Gay men.; Correspondence.; Scripts (documents); Gender identity -- United States; New York (N.Y.).; Artists and community -- United States; African Americans -- Intellectual life; African Americans |x Race identity.; Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987; Reed, Lou
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1964-08-19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1964-10-18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1965-02-15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1965-04-23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1965-10-25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1965-11-01 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1966-05-24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1966-06-16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1966-07-12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-02-26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-03-12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-03-22 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-04-29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-05-19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-06-11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-09-03 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-09-25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1967-11-02 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1968-01-30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1968-02-20 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1968-04-25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1968-06-02 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1969-04-22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1969-08-02 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1969-12-18 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1970-02-14 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1971-07-03 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1971-11-02 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1974-12-18 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1974-12-22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1975-03-08 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1975-10-11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1976-02-11 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1976-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1976-06-04 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1978-01-28 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1981-03-29 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1986-02-09 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1986-03-09 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Dorothy Dean to Joe Campbell, 1986-06-22 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Nora Sayre to Joe Campbell, 1987-02-14 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Nora Sayre to Joe Campbell, 1987-02-17 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- "Libby" to Joe Campbell, 1987-02-25 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Nora Sayre to Joe Campbell, 1987-03-25 (Box 1, Folder 46)